{"tossups": [{"question": "This man\u2019s staff doctored photos of Millard Tydings in a smear campaign. Joseph Welch attacked the\u201ccruelty\u201d of this man, who gave a speech in Wheeling, West Virginia, where he claimed to hold a list of 205 names. He was censured by the Senate in 1954 shortly after he investigated the Army in unpopular hearings. For the point, name this Wisconsin Senator who aggressively investigated Communists during the 1950\u2019s Red Scare.", "answer": "Joseph \u201cJoe\u201d<b> McCarthy</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man was saved from imminent doom by the death of empress Elizabeth, an event he called the\u201cMiracle of the House of Brandenburg.\u201d Count Kaunitz\u2019s Diplomatic Revolution helped isolate this ruler, whose sole ally became Great Britain after France defected to the side of Maria Theresa. This ruler\u2019s seizure of Silesia violated the Pragmatic Sanction and led to the War of Austrian Succession. For the point, name this \u201cgreat\u201d ruler of Prussia during the Seven Years War.", "answer": "<b> Frederick</b> the Great (or<b> Frederick</b> II)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "The<em> Gjoa</em> [g\u2019yoah] was the first ship to sail through this system, doing so over three years in the early 20th century. Jacques Cartier wrongly believed this system incorporated the St. Lawrence River. Though Roald Amundsen traversed it over a century ago, it wasn\u2019t viable as a trade route until recently. The melting of Arctic ice has helped facilitate the use of, for the point, what long-sought route to connect the Atlantic and Pacific Oceans through open Canadian waters?", "answer": "<b> Northwest Passage</b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "This ruler was nearly killed by Edward Oxford, who was deemed not guilty via insanity. This ruler, who lost a personal union with Hanover due to Salic law, was raised with the strict Kensington system and was the first to live in Balmoral Castle. In 1861, this ruler withdrew into deep mourning after the death of her husband, Prince Albert. For the point, name this \u201cgrandmother of Europe,\u201d a 19th century Queen of the United Kingdom.", "answer": "Queen<b> Victoria</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "In this city, a troubled Minoru Yamasaki public housing project was demolished on live television in 1972. This city was home to the Pruitt-Igoe project, as well as Forest Park, which hosted the 1904 World\u2019s Fair. This city is also home to the Jefferson Expansion National Memorial, best known for an inverted catenary steel structure designed by Eero Saarinen. For the point, name this Missouri city, the home of the Gateway Arch.", "answer": "<b> St. Louis</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Architecture"}, {"question": "A medieval city of this name was likely built by the Shona people and is noted for soapstone bird carvings and a Grand Enclosure. A modern country with this name gained its independence when the Lancaster House Agreement was signed by Ian Smith. Under ZANU party rule, this country\u2019s economy has suffered extreme inflation. For the point, name this successor state of Southern Rhodesia, an African country led from Harare.", "answer": "<b> Zimbabwe</b> (accept Great<b> Zimbabwe</b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Prior to this battle, a force created by Operation Cockade targeted Norway while the First US Army Group, commanded by General Patton in Operation Fortitude South, targeted the Pas-de-Calais [pah deh ka-lay]. Specially-modified tanks called Hobart\u2019s Funnies were used during this battle, which also made use of Mulberry harbors. For the point, name this battle over the Atlantic Wall in which the Allies under Dwight D. Eisenhower invaded five Nazi-held beaches in France on June 6, 1944.", "answer": "<b> D-Day</b> (or Operation<b> Overlord</b> or Battle of<b> Normandy</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This conflict began with the confiscation of the Duchy of Aquitaine. A proxy war during this conflict was the War of Breton Succession, and one side won a key naval victory at the Battle of Sluys [sloo-ees]. In this conflict, chevauch\u00b4ee [sheh-vo-shay] raids were often used by Edward the Black Prince, who won the 1356 Battle of Poitiers [pwa-tee-ay]. For the point, name this series of wars where English kings attempted to take the French crown over the course of more than a century.", "answer": "<b> Hundred Years\u2019</b> War", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man became Secretary of State following the death of Abel Upshur in the<em> Princeton</em> disaster. His wife, Floride, organized Cabinet wives against Peggy Eaton in the Petticoat Affair during the Jackson presidency. In an \u201cExposition and Protest\u201d named for his state, he claimed that states could nullify laws like the so-called \u201cTariff of Abominations.\u201d For the point, name this Vice-President and longtime Senator from South Carolina who was noted for his staunch advocacy of slavery.", "answer": "John Caldwell<b> Calhoun</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "As these people rudely invaded one event, the quip \u201cI hope we\u2019ve passed the audition\u201d was said by John Lennon; that occurred at a January 1969 concert on a rooftop, which these people stopped. Fictional examples of these people include James Japp and G. Lestrade, who are bumbling foils for Hercule Poirot [pwa-roh] and Sherlock Holmes, respectively. Jack the Ripper was notably not captured by, for the point, people of what occupation, held by the \u201cBobbies\u201d of Scotland Yard, who crack down on crime in London?", "answer": "(British/English)<b> police</b> officers (accept equivalents; accept<b> Bobbies</b> before mentioned; accept <b>Scotland Yard</b> before mentioned; prompt on general answers like \u201cEnglish people\u201d)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "A sculpture found near Kai\u2019s tomb in this country shows a scribe sitting in a cross-legged position. Elongated figures were emphasized in the Amarna period of this country\u2019s art. Mastabas were used as an early funerary structure in this country, where Imhotep designed a later type of tomb found in Saqqara. A monumental sculpture in this country is thought to be the head of Khafre with a lion\u2019s body. For the point, identify this country, home to the Sphinx and the Great Pyramids at Giza.", "answer": "<b> Egypt</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "This man moved his country towards agricultural sustainability with his Battle for Grain. This head of the Republic of Sal\u00b4o had to be rescued by Otto Skorzeny in the Gran Sasso raid. This man signed the Lateran Treaty with the Vatican, as well as the Pact of Steel. His Blackshirts assisted his rise to power during the March on Rome. Il Duce [eel doo-chay] was the nickname of, for the point, what fascist dictator of Italy?", "answer": "Benito Amilcare Andrea<b> Mussolini</b> (accept<b> Il Duce</b> before mention)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "A governor during this period, James Alcorn, supported public schools and was an ally of Senator Hiram Revels. The Wade-Davis Bill was a proposed plan for this period that was pocket vetoed by the President. During this period, Senator Thaddeus Stevens and other Radical Republicans supported programs like the Freedmen\u2019s Bureau. The South was rebuilt in, for the point, what historical period that followed the American Civil War?", "answer": "<b> Reconstruction</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "In this empire, a system of schools called the House of Youths trained commoners in warfare. Guilds of traveling merchants called pochteca operated trade throughout this empire, whose capital city used chinampas, or floating gardens, as an extra food source. This empire, formally an alliance of three city states, was ruled by Montezuma II from Tenochtitlan. For the point, name this civilization conquered for Spain by Hernan Cortes.", "answer": "<b> Aztec</b> Empire", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "This empire\u2019s navy was temporarily based with the French in Toulon after an attack on Nice [\u201dniece\u201d]. John Z\u00b4apolya contested the throne of Hungary with the support of this empire, whose domination of the Mediterranean ended at the Battle of Lepanto. This empire sieged Vienna twice and drew its janissary corps from Christian families in the Balkans. For the point, name this Muslim empire that conquered Constantinople.", "answer": "<b> Ottoman</b> Empire", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "The Jesuit priest Prospero Intorcetta translated this thinker\u2019s work into English. This man resigned after his boss was distracted by an opponent\u2019s hundred fine horses and eighty dancing girls. The concepts of<em> li</em> and<em> ren</em> are central to this man\u2019s philosophy, which was popularized after his death by disciples like Menzius and Yan Hui. The Chinese civil service system was based on the works of, for the point, what philosopher who authored the<em> Analects</em>?", "answer": "<b> Confucius</b> (accept<b> Kong Zi</b>)", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {"question": "Large portions of this country\u2019s economy are controlled by non-taxable bonyads, a system invented by a ruler who celebrated the monarchy\u2019s 2,500th anniversary in 1971. This country was led by the freely-elected Mohammed Mossadegh and the Pahlavi dynasty during the 20th century, and it became an Islamic Republic in 1979. For the point, name this Middle Eastern country currently led by President Hassan Rouhani and Supreme Leader Ayatollah Khamenei.", "answer": "Islamic Republic of<b> Iran</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "The first U.S. Minister to this country was the namesake of the poinsettia, Joel Poinsett. The essay <em>Civil Disobedience</em> described a refusal, on anti-slavery grounds, to pay taxes to support a war with this country. President James Polk advocated for the U.S. to invade this country in a war that was ended by the Treaty of Guadalupe Hidalgo. The U.S. obtained California following a war with, for the point, what neighboring country to its south?", "answer": "<b> Mexico</b> (or United<b> Mexican</b> States)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This treaty\u2019s negotiators included the \u201cHeavenly Twins\u201d and a world leader nicknamed \u201cthe Tiger.\u201dThe Dawes and Young plans tried to undo some of the damage caused by this treaty, which established Danzig as a free city but forced the Weimar Republic to pay ruinous reparations. Vittorio Orlando, Georges Clemenceau, David Lloyd George, and Woodrow Wilson debated, for the point, what problematic peace treaty that ended World War I for Germany?", "answer": "Treaty of<b> Versailles</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "This ruler defeated the Nogai and allowed the first chartered joint stock company to trade between his kingdom and England. His law code was called the<em> Sudebnik</em>, and he founded a parliament with three estates called the<em> zemsky sobor</em>. The disastrous Livonian War occurred under this ruler, who empowered the Stroganov family to conquer Siberia and killed his son in a fit of rage. For the point, name this fearsome tsar of Russia.", "answer": "<b> Ivan the Terrible</b> (accept<b> Ivan IV</b> or<b> Ivan Grozny</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}], "bonuses": []}